Bathory: Countess of Blood is a drama, fantasy film directed by Juraj Jakubisko.
Bathory is based on the legends surrounding the life and deeds of Countess Elizabeth
Bathory known as the greatest murderess in the history of mankind.
Contrary to popular belief, Elizabeth Bathory was a modern Renaissance woman who
ultimately fell victim to men’s aspirations for power and wealth.
Erzsébet Báthory, played by Anna Friel.
Juraj Thurzo, played by Karel Roden.
Ferenc Nadasdy, played by Vincent Regan.
Merisi Caravaggio, played by Hans Matheson.
Darvulia, played by Deana Horváthová.
King Mathias, played by Franco Nero.
Countess Elizabeth Báthory of Ecsed (Hungarian: Báthori Erzsébet, pronounced [ˈbaːtori ˈɛrʒeːbɛt]; Slovak: Alžbeta Bátoriová, 7 August 1560 – 21 August
1614) was a Hungarian noblewoman and serial killer from the powerful House of Báthory, who owned land in the Kingdom of Hungary (now Slovakia).
Báthory and four of her servants were accused of torturing and
killing hundreds of girls and women from 1590 to 1610.
Bathory and her cohorts were charged for 80 counts of murder and were convicted.
Her servants were put on trial and convicted.
The servants were executed, whereas Báthory was imprisoned within the Castle
of Csejte (Čachtice) until she died in her sleep in 1614.
According to scholars such as Michael Farin, the accusations against Báthory were supported by testimony from more than 300 individuals, some of
whom described physical evidence and the presence of mutilated dead, dying and imprisoned girls found at the time of her arrest.
Other scholars suggest that the accusations were a spectacle to destroy her family's influence in the region, which
was considered a threat to the political interests of her neighbours, including the Habsburg empire.
Stories about Báthory quickly became part of national folklore.
Legends describing her vampiric tendencies, such as the tale that she bathed in the blood of virgins to retain her
youth, were based on rumours and only recorded as supposedly factual over a century after her death.
Although these stories were repeated by at least three historians in the eighteenth and
nineteenth centuries, they are considered unreliable by modern historians.
Some insist that Elizabeth's story inspired Bram Stoker's novel Dracula (1897), although
Stoker's notes on the novel provided no direct evidence to support this hypothesis.
Nicknames and literary epithets attributed to her
include Blood Countess and Countess Dracula.
There are important flaws regarding modern scholarship’s attempt to
paint Elizabeth Bathory as a victim of a witch-hunt.
Firstly, Elizabeth was charged predominantly with
murder and torture, not witchcraft.
Secondly, on the night of the raid, Elizabeth Bathory was taken
into custody along with her four accomplices.
Elizabeth had accused two reverends and one pastor for the reason of her arrest, after a long
conversation where Bathory attempted to blame her accomplices for the dead bodies being found.
She added this statement after Pastor Barosius had asked her why she did not
stop her accomplices from committing the tortures and murders.
She said, "I did it ...
Because even I myself was afraid of them".
This statement was confessed by Bathory herself and
was not extracted under torture.
Critically, there were a handful of individuals who provided
first-hand accounts of Bathory's crimes at the trial.
Three of these individuals included Jakab Szivassy,
Gergely Paztory, and Benedek Deseo.
Deseo was the head of "The Lord's staff" at Castle Cjesthe and
was responsible for operations at the castle.
Since Deseo and Szivassy were around Bathory the most, they gave the most detailed
confessions of what they witnessed at their time of service at Castle Cjesthe.
It is important to note that these three men were not tortured into
confessions, unlike Bathory's accomplices (Llona, Janos, Dorrthea, etc.).
After Deseo was sworn in, he testified that Bathory "took a shoemaker's daughter named 'Illonka', stripped her naked and, in this way began to cruelly torment her by taking a knife, and beginning with the
fingers, shoved the knife into both arms up the arms, then flogging her over again, then took a burning candle to her and burned her skin, and continued to torment her until she put an end to her life".
He also testified that Bathory would "stick a sewing needle in her victims arms and use it to cut her way up the arm of a girl who could not
'sew'."
Gergely Paztory was a court judge at Castle Sarvar for Elizabeth Bathory and was forty years old when he was sworn in and testified.
He testified that a "young woman from Bratislava named Modl
accompanied Bathory and Paztory on a trip to Fuzer".
He continued, "The Lady Bathory forced her to dress up and act like a young girl, Modl pleaded for
forgiveness as she could not act like a young girl since she is already married and has a child".
Following this, in Jakab Szivassy's testimony, Jakab added that the "young woman called Modl,
since she did not want to be a girl, Bathory had cut out her flesh and roasted it".
These testimonies were collected by Mozes Cziraky and was published on 14
December 1611, in his report on the orders of King Matthias II.
The film explores themes of transylvania, legend,
greed, bratislava, slovakia, surrealism.
The tone is emotional and mind_bending.